{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This younger sister of Sybilla was dismissed as a \"great Flanders mare.\"</em> This woman lived in Richmond castle after a generous settlement. This daughter of John the Simple was wed in the Palace of Placentia, her husband's birthplace, in 1540. Because the marriage of this continental European was never consummated, she got a real annulment, unlike Catherine Howard two years later. For 10 points, name this fourth wife of England's Henry VIII, who was born in what's now Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Anne of Cleves</u></b> [or <b><u>Anna von Kleve</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>This man's name appears in the subtitle of the James Carville book \u2026and the Horse he Rode</em> <em>In On</em>.This president of Baylor University represented the school board in the case of <em>Morse v.</em> <em>Frederick</em>, also known as the \"Bong Hits 4 Jesus\" case.He created a report on the death of deputy White House counsel Vince Foster and the Whitewater scandal. For 10 points, name this independent counsel who investigated Monica Lewinsky's affair with Bill Clinton.", "answer": "Kenneth <b><u>Starr</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Practitioners of this religion traditionally drape thrones with red, white, and blue</em>. Priestly initiates of this religion must collect shell necklaces called elekes. Members of this religion were involved in the court case <em>Church of the Lukumi Babalu Aye v. City of Hialeah</em>, which dealt with the right to a certain practice undertaken in iles, or places of worship. For 10 points, name this syncretic Caribbean religion that venerates Orishas and has gained notoriety for its practice of animal sacrifice.", "answer": "<b><u>Santeria</u></b> [or <b><u>Regla de Ocha;</u></b> or La <b><u>Regla de Lucumi</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "AK"}, {"question": "<em>This leader displaced an indigenous group called the Montagnards from the Central</em> <em>Highlands in an attempt to hold back invaders.</em> Cable 243, which authorized a coup against this leader, was sent to his ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr. This man authorized the use of liquid tear gas against protesters in Hue. This man's soldiers brutally targeted his country's Buddhist majority. For 10 points, name this controversial Catholic leader of South Vietnam.", "answer": "<b><u>Ngo Dinh</u><u>Diem</u></b> [accept either]  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This waterway\u2019s Brecksville Dam feeds a historic recreational canal.</em> A national park on the banks of this river features the Towpath Trail and was declared in 1974. A 1969 event here caused by an oil slick near the Republic Steel Mill led TIME to describe it as a river where \u201cone does not drown but decays.\u201d Its most famous image was actually from a 1952 conflagration. For 10 points, what river, which empties into Lake Erie in downtown Cleveland, often caught fire?", "answer": "<b><u>Cuyahoga</u></b> River  {III}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>The most important victory of Tettius Julianus was against these people at the Second Battle</em> <em>of Tapae</em>. A war against these people spurred the formation of the Thirtieth, or Ulpia Victrix, Legion. While they were led from Sarmizegethusa by Decebalus, a bridge built by Apollodorus of Damascus helped Roman armies defeat these people by crossing the Danube en masse. For 10 points, name these rivals of the emperors Domitian and Trajan, a tribe of what's now Romania.", "answer": "<b><u>Dacian</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>Thracian</u></b>s; prompt on <b><u>Geta</u></b>e]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>The New York Times claimed that a war against this tribe was \"a gigantic blunder and a</em> <em>crime.\"</em> Yellow Wolf, a warrior of this tribe, dictated a memoir to Lucullus McWhorter. In this tribe's namesake war, it lost the Battle of Bear Paw, which occurred after warriors passed through Yellowstone National Park. In October 1877, a leader of this tribe declared \"I will fight no more forever.\" For 10 points, name this Pacific Northwest tribe led by Chief Joseph.", "answer": "<b><u>Nez Perce</u></b> [or <b><u>Niimiipu</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This object travels to Narragonia in a 1494 German satire by Sebastian Brant.</em> The start of Michel Foucault's <em>Madness and Civilization</em> discusses the popularity of this artistic motif in the Renaissance. <em>Death and the Miser</em> was probably once part of a triptych with a painting of this object by Hieronymus Bosch, in which it has a thin tree for a mast. For 10 points, name this allegorical vehicle which sails the rivers and seas of Europe with a crew of madmen.", "answer": "<b><u>ship</u></b> of <b><u>fool</u></b>s [or <em><b><u>Narrenschiff</u></b></em>]  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>Kings of this nation would take back land from the nobility in events called reductions.</em> One rebellion in this nation was led by Sten Sture the Younger. This nation\u2019s most infamous traitor is Archbishop Trolle, whose execution of rebels fighting for this country\u2019s independence encouraged the Reformation here. Rene Descartes died in this country after being invited by a queen who was nicknamed \u201cThe Minerva of the North\u201d for her interest in learning, Christina. For 10 points, name this Scandinavian nation with its capital at Stockholm.", "answer": "<b><u>Sweden</u></b> [or <b><u>Svirge</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "BA"}, {"question": "<em>This program named one plan \"Project 921\" because it was the first major project of 1992.</em> This program partnered with a European counterpart for the Double Star mission. A device developed by this initiative travelled about 375 feet across the Sea of Rains before getting stuck. This program uses a family of rockets named after a 1930\u2019s military retreat. For 10 points, identify this third national program to launch a man into orbit on the mission <em>Shenzhou 5</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Chinese space</u></b> program [or obvious equivalents]  {III}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "<em>The last house where this person\u2019s forces killed residents was owned by Rebecca Vaughan</em>. The only person this person confessed to killing was Margaret Whitehead, whom he killed with a fence post. He was captured by Benjamin Phipps after having marched towards Jerusalem in Southampton county following a solar eclipse. Thomas Gray wrote on the \u201cConfessions of\u201d [this man]. For 10 points, name this Virginian slave who led a namesake slave revolt in 1831.", "answer": "<b><u>Nat Turner</u></b> [or <b><u>Nathaniel Turner</u></b>]  {II}", "metadata": "JZ"}, {"question": "<em>A ruler of this empire annulled the Treaty of Surat and signed the favorable Convention of</em> <em>Wadgaon after the ensuing conflict.</em> This empire's military formed gangs of bandits called pindaris. This empire's founder was a member of the Bhosle clan who once escaped Agra in a basket of sweets. Shivaji was the first peshwa of this empire, which fought three namesake wars with the British. For 10 points, name this Hindu confederacy which eclipsed the Mughal Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Maratha</u></b> Empire [or <b><u>Maratha</u></b> Confederacy]  {III}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>William Dawes was a tanner and militia leader from this state</em>. In this state, Federalists built a political machine called the Essex Junto, led by former Secretary of State Timothy Pickering. One disturbance in this state was sparked by the arrival of the ships, <em>Eleanor, Dartmouth</em> and <em>Beaver</em>. Harrison Gray Otis represented this state at the Hartford Convention, to which it sent the most delegates. For 10 points, name this New England state home to John Adams.", "answer": "<b><u>Massachusetts</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A leader of this city named Smaragdus built the Column of Phocas.</em> Eutychius was the last exarch of a Byzantine client state centered on this city that fell in 751. In this city, a king who supported Leontius was stabbed to death at a banquet on the orders of the Emperor Zeno. Belisarius captured this city in 540 during the Gothic War, and Justinian and his wife were honored with a mosaic in this city\u2019s Basilica of San Vitale. For 10 points, name this city in northern Italy that was the capital of the Ostrogoths.", "answer": "<b><u>Ravenna</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A group of \u201ckayaktivists\u201d are hoping to prevent Shell Oil from using this city\u2019s port.</em> A project in this city, meant to replace a piece of infrastructure damaged in the 2001 Nisqually earthquake, has been stalled due to a steel pipe damaging a tunnel boring machine, Bertha. Its mayor Ed Murray signed a law increasing its minimum wage to $15 dollars an hour and has pushed for the replacement of the Alaskan Way viaduct. For 10 points, name this largest city in Washington.", "answer": "<b><u>Seattle</u></b>, Washington", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This person established a statistical control unit for the XX Bomber command and instituted</em> <em>systems analysis with his subordinate, Charles Hitch.</em> This Cabinet member was one of the \u201cWhiz Kids\u201d who revitalized the Ford Motor company. Errol Morris directed a documentary detailing eleven lessons from this person\u2019s life. This person commissioned the Pentagon Papers to evaluate his success fighting the Vietnam War. For 10 points, name this longest serving Secretary of Defense.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>McNamara</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This cause grew out of the earlier Language Movement and the Six-Point Movement.</em> The atrocities committed against supporters of this cause during Operation Searchlight were discussed in a telegram sent by Archer Blood. After the success of this cause, the principles of Mujibism were implemented by the leader of the Awami League. For 10 points, name this cause which sought to turn East Pakistan into an independent country with a capital at Dhaka.", "answer": "<b><u>Independence</u></b> of <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b> [or <b><u>Liberation</u></b> of <b><u>Bangladesh</u></b>; accept <b><u>Bengali</u></b> for \"Bangladesh\"; or obvious equivalents; prompt on answers like \"Bengali nationalism\"]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This person, who lost two fingers on his left hand while serving on the \u201cNisshin,\u201d was</em> <em>targeted in Operation Vengeance</em>. This former Harvard student and opponent of the Tripartite Pact supposedly said that he feared that he woke a \u201csleeping giant\u201d in his most famous action. This person was killed when his aircraft was shot down while inspecting troops in the Solomon islands. For 10 points, name this Japanese Admiral who planned the attack on Pearl Harbor.", "answer": "Isoroku <b><u>Yamamoto</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This person tabled the Clayton compromise, resulting in his stabbing by Francis Cone</em>. This person present at the Hampton Roads Conference was the friend of Robert Toombs and backed the Compromise of 1850 in a platform named for his state. He stated that slavery was the natural condition of blacks in the \u201cCornerstone Speech,\u201d and his election to the Senate in 1866 helped spur support for Reconstruction. For 10 points, name this Vice President of the Confederacy.", "answer": "Alexander Hamilton <b><u>Stephens</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man wrote a book which included a chapter on the ophicleide</em>. This composer\u2019s final symphony was written for a 200-piece wind band, and was commissioned for the tenth anniversary of the July Revolution. This creator of the <em>Treatise on Instrumentation</em> and <em>Grand</em> <em>Funeral and Triumphal Symphony</em> was inspired by actress Harriet Smithson to write a \u201cMarch to the Scaffold.\u201d For 10 points, name this composer of the <em>Symphonie Fantastique.</em>", "answer": "Hector <b><u>Berlioz</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This ruler signed the Treaty of Jam-Zapolski after Stephan Bathory invaded his country with</em> <em>forces that reached Pskov.</em> This ruler legendarily had Postnik Yakovlev blinded, and created an armed group known as the streltsy. This ruler had St. Basil's Cathedral built after this ruler's forces took control of Kazan. This ruler was succeeded by Feodor I. For 10 points, name this first tsar of Russia, who accidentally killed his son and heir-apparent.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivan</u></b> the <b><u>Terrible</u></b> [or <b><u>Ivan IV</u></b>; or <b><u>Ivan Grozny</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>During this Olympics, Hans-Gunnar Liljenwall became the first Olympic athlete to be</em> <em>disqualified for failing a drug test.</em> After winning six medals at this Olympics, Vera Caslaskva refused to deny having signed the Two Thousand Words. Ten days before its opening ceremonies, up to 300 students were killed in the Tlaltelolco Massacre. For 10 points, which Olympic Games were the first to be held in Latin America?", "answer": "<b><u>1968 Summer</u></b> Olympics [or <b><u>Mexico City</u></b> Olympics; prompt on <b><u>1968</u></b> Olympics]  At the 1968 Summer Olympics, who won the gold medal in the men's high jump by performing his namesake \"flop\"?  ANSWER: Dick <b><u>Fosbury</u></b> [or Richard Douglas <b><u>Fosbury</u></b>] {III}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em>Exceptions to this act were granted by the Webb-Pomerene Act.</em> This act was expanded to target price discrimination by the Robinson-Patman Act, and amended with a filing requirement by the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act. Since it made strikes, picketing, and boycotts legal, this legislation could not be used against labor unions as its predecessor had been. For 10 points, name this 1914 act which amended and strengthened the 1890 Sherman Antitrust Act.", "answer": "<b><u>Clayton</u></b> Antitrust Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>At a meeting of \"Volunteers Against Bolshevism,\" Paul Collette attempted to kill this</em> <em>politician.</em> This politician was the first Frenchman to be chosen as <em>Time</em> Magazine's Man of the Year. With Samuel Hoare, this man proposed a plan to appease Mussolini's desire to control Ethiopia. This man was arrested shortly after his December 1940 dismissal from Philippe P\u00e9tain's cabinet. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister of Vichy France.", "answer": "Pierre <b><u>Laval</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A chieftain of this people wielded a bow that required fifty people to operate.</u></b></em><b><u> Fifteen</u></b> <b><u>thousand members of this ethnic group, led by Barc, were baptized in 1227. Elizabeth, the</u></b> <b><u>wife of Stephen V, was a princess of this tribe. Led by Khan Konchak, this people scored a</u></b> <b><u>great victory against Prince (+)</u> Igor. This people, who formed the western branch of the Kipchak confederation, migrated westward in the thirteenth century after (*)</b> Mongol invasions threatened their homeland. For 10 points, name this nomadic Turkic people who assimilated into Hungarian society.", "answer": "<b><u>Cuman</u></b>s [or <b><u>Polovtsi</u></b>ans]  {III}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In one of this man's novels, a scholar named Barlow helps a governor's Task Force</u></b></em> <em><b><u>organize lesson plans about events such as Alvar Nu\u00f1ez Cabeza de Vaca's murder.</u> </b></em><b><u>In 1959,</u></b> <b><u>this author published a novel that ends with, and coincided with, the statehood of Hawai'i</u></b><em><b><u>.</u></b></em> <b><u>He included the indigenous trader (+)</u> Bloody Mary in a short story collection which also features an affair between Nellie Forbush and the Frenchman Emile de Becque on an (*) </b>island where American troops are stationed during World War II. For 10 points, name this American whose bulky historical fiction books include <em>Texas</em> and <em>Tales of the South Pacific</em>.", "answer": "James <b><u>Michener</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Historians sometimes call this battle the last stand of a \"Western Confederacy\" of tribes</u></b></em> <em><b><u>which included the Lenape leader Buckongahelas.</u></b></em><b><u> The Legion of the United States was</u></b> <b><u>created in anticipation of this battle. One commander at this battle had destroyed the</u></b> <b><u>forces of Arthur St. Clair at the Wabash river three years prior to it. That commander, (+)</u></b> <b>Blue Jacket, supported the Miami forces of (*) </b>Little Turtle here. The Treaty of Greenville solidified the territorial concessions following this battle. For 10 points, name this 1794 battle won by \"Mad\" Anthony Wayne over the natives of the Northwest Territory west of the Ohio River.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Fallen Timbers</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The theory in this book regards Ukraine and Yugoslavia as places on the edge of the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>\"Orthodox world.\"</u> </b></em><b><u>This book was a direct a response to, and published a year after,</u></b> <b><u>Francis Fukuyama's</u> </b><em><b><u>The End of History and the Last Man,</u> </b></em><b><u>which had predicted a</u></b> <b><u>permanent order of (+)</u> liberal democracies. This book claims that wars across a central \"fault line\" will set the (*) </b>Western and Islamic examples of the title groupings against one another. For 10 points, name this 1993 book of IR theory by Samuel Huntington, that predicted a post-Cold War world order of conflicts between large distinctive cultures.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Clash of Civilizations</u></b>and the Remaking of World Order</em>  {III}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man was accused after Newt Lee found notes referring to a night watchman as \u201cnight</u></b></em> <em><b><u>witch\u201d.</u></b></em><b><u> According to testimony from this man\u2019s office boy Alonzo Mann, Jim Conley most</u></b> <b><u>likely committed the crime this man was accused of. William Joseph Simmons revived the</u></b> <b><u>KKK after leading a group that (+)</u> kidnapped this man. After receiving a life sentence, this man was taken from prison, driven to a city near Marietta, and (*)</b> hung from a tree. The Anti-Defamation League was founded in the wake of his death. For 10 points, name this factory owner accused of killing Mary Phagan, a Jewish-American lynching victim.", "answer": "Leo Max <b><u>Frank</u></b>  {III}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>During a fire in this city, a YMCA employee named Asa Jennings saved many children as</u></b></em> <em><b><u>neutral British ships in its harbor played loud music to block out the screams.</u> </b></em><b><u>The Franks'</u></b> <b><u>Street was a center for foreign trade in this hometown of Polycarp, which was also the</u></b> <b><u>birthplace of the false messiah Shabbatai Zvi. As the Ottoman empire fell apart, irregular</u></b> <b><u>troops called (+)</u> </b><em><b>chettes </b></em><b>who answered to Mustafa Kemal razed this city in 1922, ending its long-lasting (*)</b> Greek community. For 10 points, name this coastal Anatolian city which was rebuilt by Turkey as Izmir.", "answer": "<b><u>Smyrna</u></b> [accept <b><u>Izmir</u></b> until \"Izmir\"]", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Every Queen album since 1978's</u> </b></em><b><u>Jazz</u></b><em><b><u> was recorded in this city.</u> </b></em><b><u>The album</u> </b><em><b><u>Machine Head</u> </b></em><b><u>was recorded in this city using a mobile studio owned by the Rolling Stones. \"Funky\"</u></b> <b><u>Claude Nobs, who helped audience members escape an incident in this city, was also a</u></b> <b><u>director of its famous (+)</u> jazz festival, the world\u2019s second-largest. During an incident in this city, \"some stupid with a (*)</b> flare gun\" caused a casino to burn down during a Frank Zappa concert. For 10 points, name this city on Lake Geneva, which was immortalized as the setting of Deep Purple's \"Smoke on the Water.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Montreux</u></b>, Switzerland  {III}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Captured German aircraft were offloaded into this city by the HMS Reaper as part of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Operation LUSTY.</u></b></em><b><u> Leo P. Carlin was accused of running a political machine in this city.</u></b> <b><u>The arrest of taxi driver John Weerd Smith and his subsequent dragging in front of the</u></b> <b><u>Hayes Homes project led to a (+)</u> race riot in this city during the tenure of Mayor Hugh Addonizio. Luis (*) </b>Quintana succeeded one man as mayor of this city, who received a 100 million dollar donation for this city\u2019s schools from Mark Zuckerberg. For 10 points, name this city formerly led by Cory Booker.", "answer": "<b><u>Newark</u></b>, New Jersey  {III}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This leader ordered an invasion that led to the Battle of Chains.</u></b></em><b><u> This man is sometimes</u></b> <b><u>known by his nickname of \u201cAs-Sadiq\u201d, or the truthful. This man fought the Ridda Wars</u></b> <b><u>against tribes that did not accept his authority. This man was the first to receive the title</u></b> <b><u>\u201cLeader of the (+)</u> Pilgrims\u201d when he led a party of 300 on the first Hajj conducted under Islamic Law. This man said \u201cif you worship Allah, he is (*) </b>alive and will never die\u201d at the end of a speech that began \u201cif you worshipped Muhammad, he is dead.\u201d For 10 points, name this man who Sunnis consider the first Caliph of Islam.", "answer": "<b><u>Abu Bakr</u></b> [or <b><u>Abdullah ibn Abi Qhuhafah</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "BA"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Howard Metzenbaum accused this man of never working for a living, eliciting the \u201cGold</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Star Mothers\u201d speech from this man.</u></b></em><b><u> This man, the chief author of the Nuclear Non-</u><u>Proliferation Act, defeated Mike DeWine in one election even after being named as one of</u></b> <b><u>the Keating Five. In one instance, the city of Perth turned on all its (+)</u> lights as this man passed overhead, an act which was repeated during this man\u2019s time on STS-95. His most famous accomplishment was part of the (*)</b><em>Friendship 7</em> mission. For 10 points, name this former Senator from Ohio and Mercury Seven astronaut, the first American to orbit the earth.", "answer": "John Herschel <b><u>Glenn</u></b>, Jr  {III}", "metadata": "EM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Sumio Iijima showed a molecule comprised of only this element could appear in single-</u></b><b><u>walled or multi-walled varieties.</u> </b></em><b><u>A molecule made from only this element was discovered by</u></b> <b><u>Kroto, Smalley and Curl at Rice University. Geim and Novoselov produced two-</u><u>dimensional (+)</u> layers of atoms of this element using the \"scotch tape\" method. The first (*) </b>fullerene to be discovered was sixty atoms of this element arranged in a sphere. For 10 points, name this element that completely makes up buckyballs, graphene and their namesake \"nanotubes.\"", "answer": "<b><u>carbon</u></b> [or <b><u>C</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man lost an earlobe when his golden earrings were forcibly ripped out, after which he</u></b></em> <em><b><u>was thrown in the Mamertine Prison.</u></b></em><b><u> This man seized control of his kingdom after</u></b> <b><u>murdering his half-brothers Hiempsal and Adherbal.</u><u> Sallust is known for a monograph on</u></b> <b><u>a conflict named for this king. This man lost the Battle of the (+)</u> Muthul to forces under the commander Caecilius Metellus. (*) </b>Bocchus I of Mauritania betrayed this man, who was then captured and brought to Rome. For 10 points, name this king of Numidia who waged a namesake 112-105 BCE war against the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b><u>Jugurtha</u> </b> {III}", "metadata": "CKM"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This nation gained territory from its southern neighbor during the Vienna Awards and</u></b></em> <em><b><u>overthrew its last king during the Aster Revolution.</u></b></em><b><u> One ruler of this nation was overthrown</u></b> <b><u>during Operation Panzerfaust, in which his son was kidnapped by Nazi commando Otto</u></b> <b><u>Skorzeny. Fascists in this nation joined the Arrow (+)</u> Cross Party. Though this nation has no coastline, it was ruled by Admiral Miklos Horthy who aligned it with the (*) </b>Axis in the hopes of regaining Transylvania, which this nation lost to Romania. For 10 points, name this former imperial partner of Austria, whose capital is Budapest.", "answer": "<b><u>Hungary</u></b> [or <b><u>Magyarorszag</u></b>]  {III}", "metadata": "BA"}], "bonuses": []}